Welcome to episode 12 of Under the Hood.
So this time today we are going to go
really under the hood. We are going to
talk about the AL runtime. And with me
today I have Mass. Hello Mass.
>> Thank you.
>> So tell us a little bit about yourself.
what what are you working with?
>> Yeah, so I'm mess I work on the AL
runtime in one of the server teams. Um
I'm a principal software engineer and
I've been here for
I don't know 10 12 years something like
that. I started as a student worker and
then I have actually remained in the
same team for like eight years in a row.
>> So you know a lot about uh the runtime
runtime. Yeah, I learned a lot about it,
but uh it's also impressive, right?
Because it's actually an old language
and even though the runtime has kind of
changed, a lot of the things are have
stayed the same. I mean, I'm sure you
can remember a lot from how it was back
then. And
>> you know,
>> were you there when we had Seaside?
>> Yeah. So, I actually made changes in
Seaside. I made changes in code that was
older than myself and I found that
immensely funny, right? You know,
30-year-old code and I was like, "Ah,
what is this?" But uh when I started
full-time, I think we got rid of Casside
just around that time. So almost all my
time has been in the new runtime.
>> So the AL runtime, where uh where is
that going on? Um
>> yeah, so the AL runtime is located
inside of the NST. So kind of the the
server. And when I say the server, we
actually kind of have two things we call
servers. We have the web server. Yeah.
And we have the NST or the traditional
server. Um and kind of a lot of things
runs in there but the main thing is AL
runtime and that is kind of when you
have clicked on a page you might click
an action
>> you know it goes from the browser to the
web server and then it hits the uh
>> the NST and we begin executing and uh
>> we'll you know run your code or you
there's a little bit of orchestration
before we execute the code but yeah it's
overall there.
>> So that part you're working with is the
part in the NHS. Yeah, that's the main
thing I do. There's always a few other
things like, you know, when I add a new
feature to the language, you often have
to update it in the compiler. Like you
just have to say, oh, the compiler now
knows about this.
>> Let's make sure that it knows how to
call into the NST or sometimes you add
it in the AL code that it can actually
call it or something like that. But most
of the time, yes.
>> Yeah. Okay. What does NST stand for?
>> Nation service tier.
>> All right.
>> Yeah, that was a test. That was a quick
question.
>> All right. So, so work us through what
what happened when a a line of AL code
execute. So, we talk we had another
episode with Espen when we talk about
the compiler
>> and how you know how that works and how
we generate the code and how it gets
transpired to C and all all these
things.
>> Uh but but at runtime what happens? We
have a let's assume you have a line of
code in say in a code unit. So, what's
going on? What go through the what's
going on there?
>> Yeah. Yeah. So if I can start a little
bit before that if I may, there's
actually if we think about it instead of
a line but like a block and by a block
in this case I talk about like a method.
>> Mhm.
>> So when you call a method an AL method
let's say from another AL method we have
to set up a call stack or what call a
stack frame generally. Um and and we
kind of have to set this up for a few
reasons. We do this to kind of measure
how long it took. So from start to end.
So that's an object that we just
allocate on the heap. And then we put in
a bunch of information that we use to
track. So that's that's kind of the
first thing we do. And then there's kind
of a little bit of this kind of
overhead. And then we get to executing
an actual line of code. And executing a
line of code is actually pretty simple.
Most of the time it's uh it's really
just whatever C wants to do.
>> And so it's all C# running at that
stage. Right.
>> Exactly. Right. So we have and that's
the funny thing we kind of have a you
know a runtime on a runtime right
because we are runtime but C# is also a
runtime
>> so and then from there if you look at
whatever you do let's say we do set
range on a record right then what the
runtime mostly does is it provides the
standard library so you or not standard
library actually it provides uh the
built-in functions for the language so
set range is a method that we implement
so it's called AL set range if you go
into uh the NST um and we will provide
the implementation of setting a range
right setting a filter
>> um so so that's kind of the main thing
that will happen there's a few things
about like keeping track of which record
you're doing it on but most of that is
is very implicit
>> so it's almost it's not quite an
interpreted language but a little there
it kind of had a little bit of this
flavor right yeah there's no interpreter
but there you know cuz C# is a JIT
language so the just in time compiler
>> so what you know our compiler emits is
um it takes eel and then it makes uh
well it makes ours actually makes C# and
then there's a compiler that takes the
C# and makes common intermediate
language
>> yes
>> and then the common intermediate
language the C#'s jet runtime will make
into assembly code
>> all right So, so uh lately we have done
a lot of investment in uh in to improve
performance um and more specifically uh
performance of the AL code running. So
like the idea being you know um you
wouldn't have to change you know or
partners and developers wouldn't have to
change their code or not you know uh not
always but we we'll get back to that but
uh but they would they would get you
know immediate benefit from some of the
things we learn. So take tell us a
little bit about these features and um
give a few example maybe.
>> Yeah I I think I think there's maybe a
little bit of a backstory also to be
said. I think uh you know CL or AL came
from a time where there was maybe a
little bit less focus on creating a
language that was meant for being high
performance. the language was maybe more
originally meant for being very simple
to make business logic and represent it
as easily as possible. Right? there very
much this focus on that and then over
time you know we began taking the
product into the cloud and then we began
seeing more directly kind of the impact
of running the code and from that we I
think we kind of realized okay if we got
to do that and we you know the onrem
there was maybe there's a little bit of
a hack they can do which was just buy
faster hardware right just throw more
RAM you know get a faster CPU
>> maybe even tweak the SQL or
>> exactly yeah keep SQL as close as
possible and when we went into cloud we
had to take a little bit more care of
this um which is actually good I think
cuz we we then had to do more about it
and I think we took the language and we
kind of looked again at it and said like
okay it's really nice to have this
language which is super easy to write
and like you know go to the database
it's just like one line of code right
it's amazingly smart
>> but on the other hand it also doesn't
really allow offer super optimal code in
that way because there is that
abstraction over it and uh I think in
software engineering you talk about this
concept of leaky abstractions you have
like an abstraction that's very nice and
clean but then if you want to use like
the super performant things you kind of
begin saying like well the abstraction
is this but if we know what the
underlying thing is then we can do it a
little bit faster
>> and I think in some ways we kind of did
this especially towards SQL with some of
the things. So
>> give us a few examples.
>> Yeah. So we we originally had in the
language that you know when you go on a
record and you do a a find you can do it
against we it's an abstract idea that
you can do against SQL or you could do
against a temporary table or you can do
against CRM or whatever it is right we
have multiple
>> but we kind of recognized that like if
you want to do data transfer which is
for example one of the things you did
you can only do that against SQL because
it explicitly generates a SQL query. So
we kind of began saying like ah well we
know that they almost always do it
against SQL so let's kind of leak that a
little bit. So I think data transfer is
a is a great example of that.
>> So yeah so we introduced that um a
couple of years ago I think
>> yeah so good question I think it's a
yeah it's like one and a half years now
I think something.
>> Yeah. So that that does require some
code changes right to adopt it
>> definitely.
>> Um can we see a good adoption of this?
Yeah. So data transfer uh was a re it
was actually one of those where we had a
very explicit place we wanted to use it.
Um I remember Nicola had some good
places where he wanted to use it
>> and uh we have actually slowly been
opening up.
>> Exactly right. We have slowly been
opening up more and more places. I
remember Nicolola's case cuz it was the
first one. So I remembered very vividly.
it had I think it was during upgrade
code they were trying to move some
fields
>> out of uh BAP into other and uh they he
had this case where he was trying to do
it and if he didn't use data transfer he
found the fastest SQL instance he could
get on Azure and it took three days to
do it and it timed out so it never
finished right
>> and so that was just to kind give a
little bit of
>> yeah so there what happened is that you
it's like looping through a lot of
records that was the if you don't have
the data transfer. There was no other
way exactly which is very very slow
>> and SQL has the ability to transfer
large amount of data you know natively
but we didn't really quite surface that
all the way to so that's what data
transfer basically enables right
>> yeah so when we then uptook data
transfer in that exact scenario he had I
think he had one example with 17 million
rows
>> which is a fairly large amount of data
>> from a real customer or
>> a real customer exactly and uh we then
used data transfer on it and it dropped
to 40 minutes doing the same operation
and that was just on normal database
>> so for several days to 40 minutes.
>> Exactly. I was very happy with that.
>> Yes, I was I was going to ask you so in
can you say roughly what's the uh the
factor of improvement you get with data
transfer as opposed to a you know a loop
type of implementation.
>> Yeah. I mean so it was we were trying to
establish that actually we were trying
to get like and and we kind of saw it as
if you do it on smaller tables it's it's
not a lot like if you do on 10 rows it
doesn't matter at all but when you the
it kind of it just scales linearly with
data transfer roughly and the other one
it kind of goes like this right
>> okay
>> so you really want to use it when you
have big tables I think I once looked up
in telemetry how many rows we
transferred maximum in one data transfer
>> and that was 70 million rows and that
took a few hours. I don't even want to
know how long that would have taken.
Probably not even doable.
>> Yeah, probably not.
>> So what other they we had other features
um like set load field or read isolation
which also we're targeting performance
improvement.
>> Uh so tell us a little bit about those.
Yeah. So, so set load fields we we
originally called partial records, but I
think the community has just taken to
the function name instead of the
>> the name of the feature, which is fair
enough. Um, that one it kind of came
together with a few other things. So,
set load fields requires manual uptake
in your AL code. Um, and and we have
seen quite a bit of success there. We
have some of our MVPs who really
champion it. I know Waldo is uh talking
a lot about it. I love that. Thank you.
>> Yeah.
>> And
>> suppose data transfer and set load field
they do require some code changes if you
want.
>> But set load fields is automatically
being applied if you do API calls on API
pages and that was actually where we saw
the biggest gains because those ones are
often very simple. They just read data,
right?
>> And if we could do that, if we could
limit the amount of rows or not rows,
sorry, fields you load, that is exactly
what it's great. Now, originally when we
made it, and I think this is actually an
interesting point, when we made it, it
was back when we had our old extension
model like the data storage model where
every single table extension had its own
table in SQL.
>> Mhm.
>> Um, as you probably remember, we switch
from that onto where we have a base
table and then we have a one extension
table where the companion table. Yeah.
And back when we had the old model, it
was the partial records or set load
fields was even stronger because it
could not just remove one join, it could
remove n joins in SQL, right?
>> Nowadays, I think you know removing one
join is still great and removing an
amount of fields, right? If you if you
just need to load out a single field or
two fields maybe on something like let's
say the item table that has I think 150
fields or something like that it's great
there right
>> but you know when we did the other
change it kind of changed a little bit
how important partial records or set
load fields was
>> now I would say set load fields is more
to be used in performance critical code
like where you know you're looping
through millions of rows think about it
there Yeah. Okay. Uh what about uh read
isolation?
>> Yeah. So read isolation is like one of
our newer things and um it came together
with another feature we wanted to do. We
actually it's called tri-state locking,
right? And we actually want to do
tri-state locking first but then we
swapped it around and did read isolation
first because um we got uh a lot of
feedback from internal AL developers
that they also wanted that apart from
triet locking.
>> So what is it?
>> Yeah. So um it's essentially more fine
grain control about how which which
locking semantics or or isolation
semantics do you want to read from SQL
with so back in the days there was
essentially two choices there was you
could either do read uncommitted which
is like we essentially don't care at all
about like the state of data you know
you can get dirty reads which means
>> meaning you can get like if somebody
else is in in the middle of a
transaction you might get some consists
as data or before the transaction it get
>> exactly all bets are off right it's very
fast because you don't get blocked by
other people but all bets off and then
you had you could call lock table or do
a right
>> uh modify for example and then you would
get update lock and update lock is a
pretty strict one it essentially means
like if anyone has uh read with update
lock or has done a modification then you
have to wait so that's a pretty strict
guarantee because you know if someone
calls lock table and you call lock table
and you both read, you're not allowed to
read.
>> So this was kind of the product.
>> So you get a consistent data for sure,
but you pay the price on on maybe some
locking and and and performance
eventually
>> and especially in the read scenario.
That was kind of the weird thing because
a lot of people they were like, "Oh, I
don't want to read with read uncommitted
cuz that's like all bets off, but
>> they want to read only what has been
committed. So they don't want the dirty
data. they want like they know what's
committed but they don't want to block
someone else.
>> So they kind of wanted this in between
which is generally recommitted.
>> So we wanted to give them that ability
and then we just also gave them the
other things cuz like why not do more
>> and that's what read isolation does.
>> Exactly. Yeah. It says like when you
read and it's only for reading you can
say okay do I want read uncommitted do I
want read committed
>> repeatable read or update lock
>> but you also need to specify it in the
code which which model
>> exactly so so it's kind of gives you the
ability to be more in control and I
think in general this is what we have
been doing we have been affording some
kind of flexibility or more power
>> at the cost of doing a little bit more
Um
>> but still I mean hearing you talk about
it there's still a lot of complexity in
it that it's you know abstracted for for
our developers and yeah they don't they
don't need to they need to specify what
they want but it's more like we take
care of all the all the intricate uh
things with their SQL and and making
sure all the things are are working
properly.
>> Yeah. And if we take that and say like
well what's tri-state locking then right
because tri-state locking is kind of the
companion piece for it. So as I I said
earlier, we use either redwood with red
uncommitted and then update lock. We
kind of imposed a third one. I mean you
can see my naming is very very creative,
right? We added a third one in the
middle
>> which is after a right like let's say
you call modify then you now read with
read committed instead of update lock
and then you still get this where two
people can or two different sessions can
read each other but they cannot and they
don't block each other. So that was kind
of what we wanted to achieve with
tri-state locking.
>> Have you have you seen the the effects
of this on telemetry and you know also
heard from all
>> so some of our partners are very happy
about it. I know Dulio he presented down
at I think it was last year
>> in Vienna at directions. He had a talk
there
>> and I was standing listening in you know
and at the end he was like oh and by the
way thank you miss that was very nice to
hear. So there is a there are some
really cool things there. Um I have been
trying to gather like do we see less
lock timeouts and uh it's a bit hard to
do cuz you have to we for a long time we
had tri-state as an opt-in feature
>> and then uh now it's kind of everyone is
using it but you can still disable it if
you call lock table and we still have a
lot of places that do that.
>> Yeah. Um so it's it's a bit hard to see
but in cases where we know it has been
uptaken we have seen quite a good uh and
especially read isolation we have a lot
of internal a developers who has begun
using that and really found it nice.
>> So you recommend people to who haven't
adopted and and look to to look to try
>> get that into their
>> Exactly. If you see locking issues it's
it's definitely one of those tools that
you now have in your toolbox.
>> Yeah. Yeah. And again, you know, um
maybe we quick reminder, how do we
detect locking issues?
>> Yeah. So, I mean, I think often you kind
of get it from your customers
complaining that they get this error
that like another user has uh modified
the data,
>> but telemetry is of course the partner
telemetry, right? So do we have um do we
have also have work and features which
um get performance improvements or
provide performance improvement without
requiring code uh code changes?
>> Yeah, I think in the last couple years
the best one of that is um moving from
the many table extensions to one
>> because there was just nothing our
customers had to do at all. They were
just highly under the hood.
>> Exactly. You just upgrade to the next
major. I can't remember when it was, but
it was a couple years ago. And then
>> it's just magically faster, right?
>> So, that was a great example. And it's
it's one of those things we think a
little bit about in the platform when we
think about what features do we want to
do cuz it would be lovely if all of our
features could just, you know, be
immediate. So, we have to make that
balance of like we know uptake is not
that easy. you know, we have a a lot of
AL code and it's old and some people
don't, you know, maybe they can't just
change it and stuff like that.
>> I know some of our user or like our
customers out there have something that
was developed at some point
>> and maybe the developer is no longer
there or something. So, it's of course
nicest if we can make something that's
just immediate.
>> Clearly, that's the best because nobody
needs to do anything and everybody, you
know,
>> gets a little bit happier.
>> Exactly. Exactly. So when we prepare for
this, you had you had some things you
wanted to talk about, you know, we
prepared some questions a little bit and
you say, "Okay, there's some myth we
need to bust."
>> So So tell us about it. What what do you
want to, you know, uh, I guess there are
some, you know, you get some feedback on
on on on some things and um,
>> yeah, so often it comes because like
people read the documentation or they
read the function name and then they go
like, "Oh, then it must be doing this."
And sometimes the function name was
named like 20 years ago or something.
>> So some assumption of how the runtime is
failing.
>> Yeah.
>> So a good example of that is like lock
table.
>> Yeah.
>> Lock table. I mean I think it makes
sense that it would lock the table you
know but in essence that's not what it
really does. So uh so lock table first
and foremost it doesn't actually do
anything in the moment like it doesn't
go to SQL and takes a big lock on the
entire table. What it actually does is
it says for all the future reads you're
going to do, you will do them with the
update lock hint.
>> It also does do something to the data
cache, but that's very specific. I I
don't know if we'll go into that here.
>> Um, but essentially it just means like
you can no longer read use results that
was read with a lower uh isolation
guarantee level.
>> But the major thing is that all future
reads will be with update lock.
>> Okay.
And that I don't think that's what the
name kind of suggests.
>> All right. So, any other myths you want
to while you have your audience here?
Any other myths you want to
>> Yeah. So, set current key is also a fun
one, right? Because you're thinking
like, okay, a key, you know, we have the
concept of saying, oh, there's a key in
I can specify I can say which fields and
you probably know it creates an index
and stuff like that.
>> Um, so you would probably think like,
oh, then it SQL uses it or something
like that. And SQL does support that you
could say use this index but that's not
what we do.
>> Okay.
>> What we actually do is we say um you
need to order the data like the
resulting data in the order of whatever
field you have specified.
>> It's a little bit maybe a little bit
misguiding. Uh
>> I think it is name. Yeah. Yeah.
>> You know we have talked about could we
rename it and the problem is it's kind
of hard
>> break a lot of people. Yeah.
>> Exactly. Right. So, you know, there's
also this interesting thing when it gets
to SQL that like there's actually a
pretty big implication for SQL on it,
how it queries data if you tell it to
order the data in a different way.
Because most of the time SQL will kind
of optimize for I want to read the data
that I can filter away. So, I only read
as little as possible.
>> Mh. But if you then ask it to order it
in a different order, it it kind of has
to say, okay, can I use I can maybe use
that index to read with, but then I have
to sort the data afterwards because they
wanted this ordering.
>> So sometimes with SQL will then instead
go in and choose another index that has
the right order and then read all the
data and filter it later. So it kind of
has some interesting uh performance
implications also. And I think people
>> don't think too much of that. I mean
it's also hard when the the name doesn't
suggest it.
>> So we have been trying our best to
change
>> the documentation of it to add there.
>> I also have a blog where I document some
of these kind of
>> I can I think maybe I demystify them. I
would say
>> we'll put a link in the in the comments
so you can take a look at the nice blog.
>> Um I don't do we have any other really
strange things that we have a
>> what about the temporary tables? Yeah,
temporary tables. I actually haven't
documented that on my blog. So, it's
kind of a anyone I I I remember I saw on
Twitter at some point or X I guess
nowadays where someone was guessing like
how is that actually implemented? They
were thinking maybe it's a in-memory
table but on SQL because you can do
temporary tables there or maybe it's
something else and um it's it is an
in-memory table but on the NST.
>> So, we use basically the memory of the
inst process for that.
>> Yeah. We just have a in-memory
implementation. Uh it uses the very
specific data structure called the AVL
tree which is like a classic data
structure. Uh which is kind of optimized
for searching. Uh like a red red black
tree or some of these other ones, right?
>> Um and then everything happens in memory
and uh it it is actually quite
transparent like the abstraction doesn't
leak that much. It's quite fast because
everything is in memory. Um,
and it behaves mostly reasonable, I
would say.
>> U, but it does have the implication
that, you know, the more you put in
there, the more memory you use, right?
>> Um, so it's kind of a challenge there in
some way.
>> Mhm. All right. Okay. Let's talk a
little bit about the future. What the
what do we have in store in the ENL
runtime? What should our developers look
forward to? Um,
>> yeah,
>> I mean, we don't we don't say anything
when it's going to be shipped. So, but
uh you can talk we can talk a little bit
of what we have on the on the drawing
board, right?
>> Yeah, we have some big ideas, I would
say. Right. We you know I I none of
these are actually in code. I I think
when you present down at
>> I think at tech days you normally have
this like from the labs or something
like that. And I think that one is maybe
even closer to being real. This is idea
level like this is one step before. We
don't even have it,
>> you know. Um and I I would say there's
maybe there's three things we're
thinking a lot about right now. And one
of them is uh dynamic queries.
>> Yes,
>> I've talked with so many of our MVPs
about this and they've wanted it for a
very long time
>> and we all agree it's a good idea. Um so
>> one of the problems with queries as they
are right now is that you kind of have
to write them as an AL object and
they're not really extendable. You can't
>> it's a design time decision. You can't
can't change them at one time.
>> And then they also sometimes have
feature creep. So they might have been
designed for like a very specific thing
>> but then someone comes and goes like ah
it would be nice if we could use that.
Let me just add a little bit more to it.
Right?
>> So and you know that's fine but it you
know the idea is for them to be as small
as possible and just do what you need.
Mhm.
>> So we have kind of been thinking about
like what if instead of making them at
design time you could make them at like
kind of run time. So you could say like
>> some of them.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Yeah. We would keep the old ones
of course, right? But but this new idea
would be able to say I want to read from
this base table, join in this other
table
>> and then maybe join in a third table but
I only want to do that if this record
has a value or you know some condition
is set. Right? So you can really
dynamically create them and I this is
the the name comes from there.
>> Um it's it's a challenge in the sense
that
um we want to find a good model on how
to write them because it is already
cumbersome to write a query. What if you
know if you kind of use a query builder
pattern where you say I want a designer
query then I want to add this data item
this data item this data item these
fields these fields these fields. this
becomes quite a lot of code. So we want
to find a succinct way to describe that.
>> So we're thinking a lot about like
composition. So you kind of maybe have
>> um some code that default kind of adds
what you need a lot of the time uh and
then maybe it actually becomes pretty
easy to do or another way is to go from
a record that is already instantiated
and say based on that design part of the
query. Um, we have also recently had
some talking like very recently just a
few days ago about the MCP server could
maybe you could use AI that knows about
all the tables because you know we
expose that to AI. So in the MMCP
server, it could probably use this idea
of knowing or how all the tables look to
generate just what it needs to look up.
>> And
>> but we would need to have the ability to
generate queries on the fly to start
with, right? But then I mean like the
addition of MCP servers and AI would be
a great combination because you could
express things maybe even in natural
language and then create queries on the
fly or
>> or or even programmatically. Yeah, we're
thinking about like maybe the MCP is a
good way to start testing it out to see
how it works
>> because if that one is missing
something, we often find that like you
can add more metadata or like better
documentation that will also help you
know the average user right average
developer out there.
>> Um so we might experiment with it there
first and then get some learnings and
then take it to AO.
>> All right. Um yeah, so that's the first
thing we've been thinking a lot about.
Uh there's some more there's a
conceptual idea which I like to call
bulk events.
>> Yeah.
>> And that comes from um we have delete
all and modify all uh which is a great
like one of those it's a league
abstraction actually. It's one of those
places where we can ask SQL instead of
row like line by line or row by row to
do like delete you know you do a find
set and then delete one row at a time we
can kind of say delete all that matches
these filters
>> but we have the problem that since AL is
rowby row based you can go in and set a
on after modify trigger or on before
modify on before delete
>> and that will often generate a lot of
events. Yeah. And and you know if you
have that then we actually say well then
we can't use the bulk statement. We
can't just do one big delete. Then we
fall back to doing the rowby row
deletion
>> and that's very slow like
>> for performance. Yeah.
>> Exactly. Performance. Um and if we could
do what we call a bulk event. So we
could say
>> okay you want to kind of subscribe and
do something. Well, what if we gave you
the ability to subscribe on not rowby
row but like on the bulk delete or bulk
modify. So you instead of you know
getting an event for each row that gets
modified you get to know okay we've
modified this this
>> the filters that match that
>> one event instead
>> and then we wouldn't have to fall back
to the rowby roast approach
>> like I I actually just recently talked
with one of our internal developers who
had a a performance case from a customer
and the problem was exactly that it fell
back to this rowbyrow approach and then
it got super slow. So that's one of
those things we would love to do and
with that we also would love to if we
could move a little bit away from rowby
row to doing you know set based things
which is what SQL is meant for
>> like you know it's a set based language
and that's where it's really fast. So if
we could take more and more and move it
towards set like if you if you're used
to C# you might have this idea of link
which is like you do where this then do
that right if we could in some way have
that nail that would be a very strong
concept
>> now it would probably be quite a big
change to ale
>> but that's one of those big ideas we'd
like to get towards
>> so some things to look forward to
>> yeah and this is not next release or the
one after this is like
>> but I mean it's this one time. It needs
constant uh evolution and we keep adding
to it and improving it, right?
>> Yeah.
>> Um so if you had if you had one thing
you you you wanted to redesign about the
the current runtime. So one thing you
would say, you know, hey, when you come
to work every day, you look at this
runtime, ah there's this thing, you
know, I wish I could rewrite it, right?
>> What would that be?
Yeah, it's it's um there's maybe a few
things, but uh I do think fundamentally
if we could go back and say the rowbyrow
like what we just talked about
>> that would probably be the biggest
performance change especially when you
do big datadriven things right if you
just open a page and show 50 rows
doesn't matter it's fine
>> but when you we do for example um
upgrade code units that often touch a
lot of stuff.
>> They're doing things row by row is
really hurting us. So that's that's
probably one of those things.
>> Uh that's the biggest kind of would
really change that type of operations.
But kind of in the day-to-day things, it
probably wouldn't change so much
performance like opening a page for
sure. I think in the open page scenario
it's probably
um maybe more the fact that we do so
many triggers. Um, so I think uh often
we do the the you can do the on after
get current record which just does one
trigger execution when you open a page
but you can also here we're talking a
list page so you can do on after get
record I think it's called and the on
next trigger
>> cuz because they execute every single
time um if you have those ones and you
begin putting logic in there it can
become very expensive. Um, we we have
seen quite often when they have slow
page openings, it can be because they
have added a lot of logic in there. So
that's I guess also a little bit of a
rowbyrow thing actually.
So I mean that's the big dream. If you
could change that, that would have been
cool.
>> All right. Uh before we conclude, do you
have any word of advice for partners and
developers? you know what what should
they do to if they want to leverage all
the you know great stuff you've just
talked about uh in a runtime
>> yeah I I think maybe the first thing is
they should do is figure out what their
hot path code is and by that I mean
figure out like is this something that
gets executed you know 10 times a day
>> or 10,000 times a day or maybe millions
of times a day
>> because if you find those ones you can
we have now added things in the toolbox
what I've been talking about earlier,
right? And if you know that these paths
here are your really hot path codes, um,
and they change from scenario to
scenario, of course, but you know, if
you if you analyze these ones and you
get down to, okay, this is where we have
to be a little bit careful,
>> then you can begin putting in your
effort, you know, I think you should
start with something like um the
profiler, sampling profiler. That one
can be a good tool. Uh I think sometimes
developers have this idea of what is
slow and then when they actually run a
profiler they figure out oh wait a
second there was actually somewhere
else. I mean I have done that many times
right? Um so I think if you start there
you get down to like just these like
maybe functions here or something like
that. Then you should begin applying the
things in that have come in the toolbox.
And this is not just the things we've
talked about today. There's also stuff
like the dictionary data type which in
some cases can replace the temporary
tables. Temporary tables is great also
>> but if you need the quickest just check
if there's a there or just look up that
value.
>> So dictionaries are better.
>> Dictionaries is way better you know
asically it's
>> uh it's login versus constant time if we
are to be nerdy. Um so so I would
definitely you know start by narrow it
down and then you know look in the
toolbox find the great tools that we
have added over time and try to apply
them.
>> Um I think for example set load fields
we have had great experience especially
if you are only in read scenarios and
you're reading millions of lines of rows
uh that can really help you out there
for example. All right. Well, thank you,
M. That was really under the hood. So,
let us know in the comment if you want
to hear. We could talk about that for,
you know, hours, right? There's a lot
more things into what's going on in the
NHD and the runtime. So, let us know in
the comment if you want what you would
like to hear about and uh, you know, I
make a new episode about it. Um, thank
you, Matt, and thank you for watching.
>> Thank you.